Register of the Aubrey Wray Fitch papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aubrey Wray Fitch papers
1900-1982
80132
Hoover Institution Archives
4 manuscript boxes, 6 oversize boxes, 2 sound discs (5.2 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches, orders, personnel records, clippings, and photographs collected by Aubrey Wray Fitch relating to American naval aviation, especially in the Pacific Theater during World War II. Sound use copies of sound recordings available.
Fitch, Aubrey Wray, 1883-1978.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1883 June 11 Born, St. Ignace, Michigan
1906 Graduated, United States Naval Academy
1908 Ensign, United States Navy
1930 Received wings, Naval Aviator
1931 Commander, USS Langley, United States Navy's first aircraft carrier
1942 Vice Admiral, United States Navy Awarded Distinguished Service Medal for leadership role during the Battle of the Coral Sea
1942-1944 Commander, Air Forces, South Pacific
1944-1945 Deputy Chief of Naval Operations (Air)
1945-1947 Superintendent, first aviator appointed to the United States Naval Academy Annapolis, Maryland
1947 Retired as Admiral, United States Navy
1978 May 22 Died, Newcastle, Maine
Scope and Content of Collection
The Aubrey Wray Fitch papers consist of the personal and naval records of Admiral Fitch. These papers document the span from his early career as a student at the United States Naval Academy, circa 1902, to the launching of the guided missile frigate USS Aubrey Fitch (FFG-34) in 1981, three years after his death. While the collection primarily emphasizes American naval aviation in the Pacific Theater during World War II, with special focus on the Battle of the Coral Sea, it also documents Admiral Fitch’s time as Superintendent of the United States Naval Academy from 1945 to 1947.
As a Vice Admiral in the Pacific Theater during World War II, Fitch commanded U.S. planes in the Battle of the Coral Sea, the first naval battle fought entirely by aircraft. Although his flagship, the USS Lexington, was sunk during the battle, Fitch was praised for his leadership and was awarded the Distinguished Service Medal. The Naval Records series includes Fitch’s naval awards, orders and promotions, dispatches, war diaries from the Pacific Theater during World War II, and poems and drawings created by fellow sailors. Photographs within the collection depict the early stages of U.S. naval aviation and follow Fitch throughout his changing assignments. The collection also contains personal scrapbooks created by Fitch during his time in the Navy.
In 1945, Fitch became the first naval aviator to be appointed Superintendent of the U.S. Naval Academy. Fitch served as Superintendent until 1947, when he retired with the rank of Admiral. The Speeches and Writings series contains award presentations, written press releases, and speeches made by Fitch at the U.S. Naval Academy, including his retirement speech.
Unless otherwise noted, the arrangement scheme was imposed during processing in the absence of an identifiable original order.
United States. Navy--Aviation.; United States. Navy--Officers.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Pacific Ocean.; Sound recordings.
- Correspondence, 1941-1971 (Box 1)
  Scope and Content
  Original alphabetical order of correspondence was maintained.
  - A-B, 1944-1959 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - C-D, 1944-1971 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - E-F, 1944-1947 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - G-I, 1944-1959 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - J-M, 1945-1964 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - N-Q, 1944-1959 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - R-S, 1943-1947 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - T-Z, 1941-1967 (Box-folder 1: 8)
- Speeches and Writings, 1919-1947 (Box 2)
  Includes radio broadcast transcripts, awards presentations, written press releases, and speeches made at the U.S. Naval Academy while Fitch was Superintendent, arranged in chronological order.
  - Award presentations, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Introduction of Rear Admiral Lewis B. Combs, undated (Box-folder 2: 2)
  - Naval Academy lecture, 1919 March (Box-folder 2: 3)
  - Army Air Force awards presentation, 1942 October 9 (Box-folder 2: 4)
  - Enterprise awards presentation, 1943 January 22 (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Task Force Sixty-seven awards presentation, 1943 January 26 (Box-folder 2: 6)
  - Tangier awards presentation, 1943 February 20 (Box-folder 2: 7)
  - Presentation of Distinguished Service Medal to Major General Patch, 1943 March 10 (Box-folder 2: 8)
  - Retention of land-based planes, after 1944 (Box-folder 2: 9)
  - Visit from Soviet airmen, 1944 May 30 (Box-folder 2: 10)
  - 31st anniversary of naval aviation, 1944 August 29 (Box-folder 2: 11)
  - Navy Day, 1944 October 27 (Box-folder 2: 12)
  - Edwin C. Hill broadcast, 1944 October 31 (Box-folder 2: 13)
  - Introduction to Commodore Burke, 1944 November 16 (Box-folder 2: 14)
  - By others, 1944-1945, undated (Box-folder 2: 15)
  - National Plastic Products Company, circa 1945 (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - The Naval Academy as it begins its second century, circa 1945 (Box-folder 2: 17)
  - Acceptance of ensign presented by civilian employees, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 18)
  - Board of Visitors, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 19)
  - Centennial issue of The Log, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 20)
  - Commissioning of USS Princeton, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 21)
  - "I Know the Enemy" radio series, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 22)
  - Memorial dedication, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 23)
  - "Unsung Hero" radio program, 1945 (Box-folder 2: 24)
  - "Navy and Marine Pilots Outshoot Japanese,", 1945 February 3 (Box-folder 2: 25)
  - Press conference, 1945 February 7 (Box-folder 2: 26)
  - To the employees of Grumman, 1945 April 10 (Box-folder 2: 27)
  - V-E Day, 1945 May 8 (Box-folder 2: 28)
  - USS Franklin tribute, 1945 May 21 (Box-folder 2: 29)
  - Proposed statement on universal military training, 1945 June 16 (Box-folder 2: 30)
  - "Navy Hour" broadcast, 1945 July 24 (Box-folder 2: 31)
  - Acceptance of Order of the Southern Cross, 1945 July 25 (Box-folder 2: 32)
  - Reserve battalion review, 1945 August 23 (Box-folder 2: 33)
  - Captain John Madison Hoskins, 1945 August 23 (Box-folder 2: 34)
  - Press luncheon, 1945 September 1 (Box-folder 2: 35)
  - "Saga of USS Maryland,", 1945 September 11 (Box-folder 2: 36)
  - To the brigade of midshipmen, 1945 September 20 (Box-folder 2: 37)
  - "Meet Your Navy" program, 1945 October 1 (Box-folder 2: 38)
  - Navy Day, 1945 October 25 (Box-folder 2: 39)
  - Maryland's victory loan, 1945 October 30 (Box-folder 2: 40)
  - Last graduating class of midshipmen from Notre Dame, 1945 November 2 (Box-folder 2: 41)
  - Introduction of Admiral Halsey, 1945 November 27 (Box-folder 2: 42)
  - Unification at St. John's Military Academy, 1945 December 20 (Box-folder 2: 43)
  - Visit to Victoria, British Columbia, circa 1946 (Box-folder 2: 44)
  - 141st anniversary of Trafalgar, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 45)
  - June Week, 1946 (Box-folder 2: 46)
  - USS Kearsarge, 1946 March 2 (Box-folder 2: 47)
  - Broadcast to the people of the Philippine Islands, 1946 April 22 (Box-folder 2: 48)
  - Board of Visitors, 1947 (Box-folder 2: 49)
  - United Citizens League, 1947 January 1 (Box-folder 2: 50)
  - Naval academy resignation, 1947 February 15 (Box-folder 2: 51)
- Naval Records, 1908-1982 (Boxes 3-4)
  Includes flight log books, naval correspondence, orders and promotions, war diaries, and poems and drawings created by fellow sailors. Also includes documentation of the launching of the guided missile frigate USS Aubrey Fitch (FFG-34) in 1981. Records are arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Aviators flight log book, 1942-1947 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1942, 1945 (Box-folder 3: 2)
  - Correspondence, 1943 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  - Drawings, undated (Box-folder 3: 4)
  - Excerpts from personal papers, 1908-1974 (Box-folder 3: 5)
  - Launching of the USS Aubrey Fitch (FFG 34), 1981-1982 (Box-folder 3: 6)
  - Orders and promotions, 1908-1919 (Box-folder 3: 7)
  - Orders and promotions, 1921-1939 (Box-folder 3: 8)
  - Orders and promotions, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Orders and promotions, 1945-1953 (Box-folder 4: 2)
  - Poems and lyrics, undated (Box-folder 4: 3)
  - War diaries, 1942 (Box-folder 4: 4)
- Printed Matter, 1906-1963 (Boxes 4, 9)
  Includes awards presented to Fitch, clippings, U.S. Naval Academy souvenir books and bulletin, and naval yearbooks, arranged in alphabetical order.
  - Awards, 1919-1959 (Box-folder 4: 5)
  - Clippings, 1936-1963 (Box-folder 4: 6)
  - Lucky Bag, 1906 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - Naval Academy Bulletin, No. 9, 1956 June (Box-folder 4: 7)
  - Naval Academy Centennial, 1945 (Box-folder 4: 8)
  - Naval Academy Souvenir Book, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 9)
  - Trident, 1946 (Box-folder 4: 10)
  - USS Wyoming: At War in the North Sea, 1917-1918 (Box-folder 4: 11)
- Photographs, 1902-1978 (Boxes 5-6)
  Includes photographs of Naval bases, naval aviation, President Roosevelt’s visits to Pensacola, the U.S. Naval Academy, the Pacific Theater during World War II, and Fitch’s personal life after retirement, arranged in chronological order. Photocopies of images are also included.
  - Undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
  - 1902-1915 (Box-folder 5: 2)
  - 1932 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  - 1933-1935 (Box-folder 5: 4)
  - 1936-1938 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  - President Roosevelt's visits to Pensacola, 1938 June - 1940 April (Box-folder 5: 7)
  - 1940 (Box-folder 5: 8)
  - 1941-1942 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - 1943 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - 1944 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - 1945 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - 1946 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - 1947 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - 1955-1978 (Box-folder 6: 7)
- Scrapbooks, 1900-1943 (Boxes 7-10)
  Scrapbooks documenting Fitch’s naval career from his time as a student at the U.S. Naval Academy to his station as Vice Admiral in the Pacific Theater during World War II, arranged in chronological order.
  - 1900-1904 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - 1906-1908 (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - 1910-1936 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - 1918 (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - 1922-1926 (Box-folder 9: 2)
  - 1941-1942 (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - 1941-1943 (Box-folder 10: 1)
- Sound Recording, 1947 January 15 (Record cabinet)
  Access
  Use copy reference number: 80132_a_0002815
  Sound recording of ceremony noting the changing of command for the U.S. Naval Academy. Includes speeches by the outgoing head, Admiral Aubrey Wray Fitch, and incoming head, Admiral James L. Holloway, Jr., as well as a gun salute and the thoughts of Captain Long.